[Music]
hey everybody
i'm connor from polyglossa.com
welcome to this free listening practice
seminar
at polyglossa.com we have
one dollar seminars every week
we have seminars for listening for
pronunciation
and for other subjects too today
you get to see a free listening practice
seminar
so let's get started at the beginning
of every listening practice seminar
we always review the four essential
elements of english listening
comprehension
those elements are stress
reduced speech linking and
phoneme distinction so
if you want to improve your listening
skills
in english you need to improve
in these four areas okay
so let me show you an example of
each one all right i'm going to show you
an example sentence my
parents make
and effort
okay so first let's
look at the stress in this sentence
in english stress refers to
how long and loud we
say each syllable or word
right so if a word or a syllable
is stressed we say it longer
and louder so listen as i say this
sentence
and try to identify the stress you ready
my parents make an effort my parents
make an effort
listen again and watch my hand my
parents
make an effort my parents make an
effort you hear the stress
we have stress in this word my parents
in this word make and
in this word effort however
these two words do not receive stress
so we don't say them very loudly
or we don't say them for a long
time right listen again my
parents make an effort so that
is an example of stress reduced speech
is what happens when the words that
are unstressed become reduced
they become shorter and faster
and their pronunciation changes
we have one example of that in this
sentence
this word right here an
is not pronounced and it's
reduced this word is unstressed
so it's reduced it sounds
kind of like this word
listen again my parents make an effort
make an effort make an effort
do you hear that word it sounds like in
right making make an effort we don't say
make an effort no native speaker says
that
we say make an effort
make an effort right that's an example
of reduced speech you have to expect
that
when you're listening next we have
linking linking is what happens
when we have a word that ends with a
consonant
sound and the next word starts with a
vowel sound
for example here we have a word that
ends with a consonant
sound k right make
the e is silent right make
the next word starts with a vowel sound
in so what happens
the consonant from the end of this word
goes to the vowel at the beginning of
the next word
so we don't say make in
effort we say may
can effort right we carry the consonant
to the next vowel not make in
may can make an effort
make an effort make an effort
here we have the same thing the n
the consonant goes to the next
vowel in effort nefert
the n goes to the next vowel
that is linking lastly
phoneme distinction a phoneme is
a sound a sound is a phoneme so
when i say phoneme distinction i mean
that you need to be able to distinguish
between different sounds so for example
in the word parents we have this sound
air right most students
when they're at a beginner level or
maybe an intermediate level
they pronounce this word as parents
par right like the word
hard they see ar and they say
are parents that's not correct
native speakers do not say parents
we say parents air
like this word air
so if you're expecting to hear this
sound
par parents you're not gonna understand
this word when we say it with the
correct sound
air parents right
so that's an example of phoneme
distinction
so these are the four essential elements
that you need to improve if you want to
improve your listening skills so now
we're going to look at a target
paragraph
i'm going to write a paragraph here and
we're going to
analyze that paragraph for these
four elements to see why
it's difficult for you to understand the
paragraph
when you hear it okay but before i
write our paragraph on the board i'm
going to read it
first and we'll see how much you can
understand
you ready only adults enjoy espresso and
other types of coffee
i'll see if we have any so that you can
taste it but you won't like it
i tasted at the age of four and it was
an utter disaster all right
how was that did you understand it
that's ok if you didn't
that's why we're here to practice your
listening
so i'm going to say it one more time and
this time
you can read it ready only adults enjoy
espresso and other types of coffee
i'll see if we have any so that you can
taste it but you won't like it
i tasted it at the age of four and it
was an utter disaster
okay how was that was that a little bit
easier maybe a little bit right
well now we're going to analyze
this paragraph for those four essential
elements
that we talked about to see why
it's difficult for you to understand
these sentences when a native speaker
says them
so let's get started looking at it
phrase by phrase
so firstly the first two words only
adults only adults
so notice here in this second word
where the stress is listen again
adults adults
it's obviously in the second syllable
right
adults adults
so this first syllable here
this a at the beginning
is not pronounced normally it's
reduced because it's unstressed
so instead of saying adults
we say adults this
sound is what we call the
schwa sound this is the most
important sound in english because
it's the most common vowel sound
listen again
for example when we have the word
about about
or the word
occur occur
do you hear that schwa sound
about occur
adults this sound
happens when a syllable is unstressed
and reduced it doesn't matter which
vowel we have
a o e i u
it doesn't matter any vowel can become
the schwa sound when it's unstressed
so you need to be careful when you're
listening
because many students of mine
when i say this word adults
they say to me what's adults what does
dolts mean and i say no not dolts
adults that sound
is said so fast that they can't hear it
they think i'm saying doltz but i'm not
i'm saying uh adults adults
that's why it's very important to
identify
this schwa sound when you're listening
so
only in only adults only adults
we don't say adults we say adults
same thing with this next word here with
this word
which syllable is stressed enjoy
enjoy the second syllable right
the first syllable is unstressed
and it's reduced we don't say enjoy
we say enjoy i enjoyed it
it sounds more like in not
en right enjoy enjoy
it's very very fast right it's
reduced okay so adults
enjoy and the next word espresso
we don't say espresso we say
espresso that same
schwa sound right espresso
espresso because this syllable
is unstressed and reduced right
so all three of those words
have the same pattern adults enjoy
espresso only adults enjoy espresso
if you listen to a native speaker and
you hear that phrase
you might only hear the second syllable
doltz joy espresso
right so you have to be really careful
and listen
for that schwa sound okay so next we
have
an other so
when a native speaker speaks english
they almost never stress this word
the word and is usually not stressed
right it becomes unstressed and
reduced so we say it kind of like this
in right only adults enjoy espresso
another another another
we don't say and other because
this word is not stressed another
another so it becomes the schwa
sound reduced
another another right
we don't try to make this sound as
native speakers
it comes out naturally because
it helps us get the right stress on the
next word
another if we say and other
you can't hear where the stress is
and in english the stress is the most
important element
of the pronunciation system so we always
want to get the correct
stress that's why the schwa sound
occurs so much because we reduce
the unstressed syllables and unstressed
words
another you need to be careful because
this sounds
like this word another
it's pronounced the same way another
another
so if you're not aware of this
when i say this phrase you might hear
this word right so you've got to be
careful
you have to remember that this word and
is always reduced another
another okay so only adults
only adults enjoy espresso and other
types of coffee
types of coffee other types
of coffee so when native speakers
say this phrase at normal speed
they don't say types of coffee
right the stress is only
on these two words types of coffee
types of coffee types of coffee
you hear that this word is unstressed
right and in certain phrases
when the word of is unstressed
it just becomes the schwa sound it just
becomes
uh or kind of like the word uh
right listen again types of coffee
types we don't even say the f
types of coffee right if we say this
phrase
right here this
would be said cup of coffee we don't say
cup of coffee we say kappa cup of coffee
i want a cup of coffee different types
of coffee
you hear that the word of becomes
reduced
to the schwa sound types
and notice our linking here right the
ending s goes to the beginning vowel
right
or the s goes to the next word and it
becomes
you hear that that's linking all right
okay and other types of coffee let's go
ahead with the next sentence so next we
have this contraction
all this contraction
is not pronounced io
no native speaker says this listen again
as i say it
i'll see i'll see
i'll see it becomes
[Music]
this sound all i'll see
i'll go i'll do i'll try
you hear that we don't say i'll we say
all because these contractions
are not stressed they're unstressed and
reduced
right so we don't say i'll see
we say i'll see i'll see
i'll do i'll try it's unstressed
right you need to be careful because
when we say this word
it sounds like this word so if you're
not expecting that
you're going to think that i'm saying
this word all
all like a-l-l but no
i'm saying i'll right i
don't say that at normal speed i say oh
all c okay i'll see if we have any
i'll see if we have any let's look at
this next part
if we have
any i'll see if we have any first
let's look at the stress i'll see if we
have any
i'll see if we have any so c
and have are stressed right
so that means the other words have the
possibility to be unstressed and reduced
see if we these words are pronounced
relatively
the same way you would think i'll see if
we
i'll see if we see if we have any but
what happens with this word here
we don't pronounce it as any right
it kind of becomes like this
so listen again have any have any
i'll see if we have any this a
becomes reduced right not
any
so sometimes when i say this phrase
my students think i'm saying this word
or this contraction have it
i say have any and they say they think
i'm saying haven't.
listen to the difference haven't
have any you need to be careful because
they sound
similar except for this last y right
haven't have any you need to expect
this word to be reduced we don't say
any day say any day i can go any day
any any it sounds much faster right
so at the end of this word it becomes
even faster
and we say have any have any i'll see if
we have any
have any right you got to be careful
with that
because it kind of sounds like this
contraction right
so i'll see if we have any so that you
can taste it
so that you can taste it so
that you
can i'll write it here taste
it all right so that you can taste it
this phrase or this group of words is
pronounced very fast right
so let's look at why that happens first
let's look at the stress
so that you can taste it so that you can
taste it
so that you can taste it right we have a
little stress here
and we have stress here so that you can
taste it
so that you can taste it so the other
words
can become reduced possibly right
this word is fine so but what happens
with this word
we don't say that so
that that it becomes reduced to
the i know that i know that he's here
that i don't say i know that he's here
i know that i know that he's here
i know that you're mad i know that
you're mad that
we don't stress this word in this
structure
if you say that you are
indicating something that light
that clock that wall but
here we're not doing that we're
introducing
other information so this word is not
stressed
we don't say so that you can
so that so that you can notice here
that the word can is also not pronounced
can right it's pronounced
[Music]
right this is very important because
can and can't
[Music]
are pronounced very differently in our
sentences
right i don't say i can go
i say i can go can
is not stressed in our sentences
we say i can i can i can
he can you can weaken we can go
he can go i can go you hear that
however this word right here can't
is stressed so i can't go
he can't go we can't go
big difference right i can go
i can't go big difference
so don't expect to hear native speakers
say can we don't say that we say
[Music]
right so that you can go i forgot to
mention this right here
what happens when a word ends with a t
and the next words is you your yo
yours listen again so that you
so that you can go so that you can do so
that you can see
so that you can taste the chew i know
what you did
what do we have a ch sound
this is reduction right the chew
so that you can the chew can we don't
say
that you can the chu the chuken
this happens all the time in english
okay
i know that you i know what you what you
the true okay so that you can taste it
notice here that this combination of
words
might sound a little bit like this for
some students
taste it taste it the difference
is that here we have a t sound and it's
just it like this there's no
vocal chord activation here
there is tasted
i'm activating my vocal cords here i'm
not
so listen again taste it taste it
do you hear that vocal cord activation
tasted
so be careful because here later we're
gonna see
the other word tasted right okay
so that you can taste it so that you can
taste it
let's go ahead with our next phrase
here but you won't like it but you
we just saw this when a word ends with
the t
and the next word is you your yours yo
etc this becomes a ch
so it becomes like this
we don't say but you we say bachu
right but you won't like it but you'll
have to wait
but you're not going to see it but you
but you're
butchered right so make sure
you expect to hear that right don't
expect to hear that you but you
really notice when you listen to native
speakers
that we combine these letters to make a
ch
but you really notice that when you're
listening
okay all right but you won't like it
you won't like it right this is fairly
easy to understand i think
but i just want to i just want to point
out the linking
like it like it all right so
the k is the final sound here it's a
consonant
like and the next word starts with a
vowel
right like it like it so here
we don't say like it we say lie
kit so some students
they might think i'm saying liked
because they think that this word
is pronounced liked and they'll think
like it
like it no this word is not pronounced
liked
it's liked liked this phrase is
like it like it you hear that
all right but you won't like it let's
move on here
i tasted it all right remember i showed
you that
we don't uh we don't pronounce these two
the same way
even though it might sound like that for
you
uh this is tasted
and this is taste it it no vocal cords
there right
it's silent so taste it taste it
right i tasted it here we have
the next word it so the final consonant
goes to the next vowel tasted it
tasted tasted it
tasted it right that might be a little
weird for you
to hear but that's how we say it tasted
it
tasted it i tasted it i
tasted it at the age of four so here
this next word
is also reduced right i
tasted it the age of four i tasted it
the age of four
right so this word has stress this word
has stress
and this word has stress but the other
words
don't have that same stress so they can
be reduced
this is a good example of that this word
is pronounced
exactly like this word so i tasted it
it the eat the age right if i say
this phrase right here
i don't say at the mall i say
at the mall i'm at the mall
he's at the mall it it it
the a becomes reduced right it
because of the schwa sound right at the
mall
i tasted it at the age tasted it it
it same thing practically right
at the mall at the age so
this word is stressed this word is not
right at the mall
at the age i tasted it at the age of
four
the age of four so let's look at this
next
phrase here the age of four
of four so
notice that here we have the number
right
four the age of 4 right
however when it comes to this word right
here
we do not stress this word so
some students they might get confused
with the difference between
four and four there should be no
confusion
because this word is stressed four
i have four brothers i have four dogs
this word is not stressed so
this let me write this phrase this
is oops
wrong word this is
for you i don't say
this is for you nope we don't say
four this is for
this is for you this is for me
this is for him it's pronounced like
this
[Music]
it's reduced it's said very fast
right so you need to identify the
difference
in those sounds four right
four versus fur
four fur i'm four years old
this is for you so you should never get
confused
between those words okay they're
different
phonemes all right so i tasted at the
age of four
at the age of four and it was an utter
disaster
so here we have and it was
remember with the word and did we see
that yeah
up here the word and becomes reduced
right and it was
and it was we don't say and it was
in it in it and it was we have linking
here
the n goes to the next vowel
init we don't say in it
in it so it sounds like we're saying
this phrase right in it
right be careful because you
you shouldn't understand or you
shouldn't interpret it as this phrase
if we say this phrase and it was and it
was
we're not saying init we're saying and
it
and it was an utter disaster was in
notice here we also reduced the word an
to in and it was in it was in
and we have linking right the final
uh consonant goes to the beginning vowel
was
in was in and it was in
was in so this word
sorry this word this word and this word
are all pronounced the same in english
in
in same right and it was
in it wasn't and it wasn't and it was an
utter disaster so we're almost done here
let me just show you this last phrase
another disaster
so another an utter disaster
utter just means complete it was a
complete
disaster a total disaster so here i want
to point out first the linking
the final n with the beginning vowel
another
another right and notice that this word
might be misinterpreted and you might
think i'm saying this word another an
utter
another many students might think i'm
saying
another disaster but i'm not listen
again
an utter disaster what's the difference
we have a different phoneme here okay
this is a d sound
utter water bottle
udder this is that
voiced th sound
the vibrated th like
the these this right be careful
because if you're a speaker of a certain
language
maybe you don't have both of these
sounds
in your language and you hear them the
same way
but they're not the same sound utter
other notice my tongue utter other
right a different phoneme an utter
disaster
another disaster okay so we
finished analyzing our target paragraph
here
so just to review
let's say it one more time and let's see
if it sounds
a little bit easier for you to
understand
you ready only adults enjoy espresso and
other types of coffee
i'll see if we have any so that you can
taste it but you won't like it
i tasted it at the age of four and it
was an utter disaster
how was that was that a little bit
easier this time
it might still be hard for you and
that's okay
the point of these seminars is not for
you to
understand the paragraph perfectly right
i'm trying to help you identify
those four essential elements the stress
the reduced speech the linking and the
phoneme distinction
when you're listening so i want you to
take
those elements those patterns
and apply them to your own listening
practice
really listen for the stress listen
for the reduced speech for the linking
and the different phonemes
right for example when you hear this
word now
you shouldn't expect to hear and
you should expect in same with this one
in orange in apple you should expect
to hear that correct reduced sound
so that's just in one example you can
take
many examples from this paragraph
so if you liked this seminar please
consider joining our one dollar
listening practice seminars
at polycloset.com we have seminars
every week and each one is only one
dollar
and we do this we practice just like we
practice
in this free seminar so i hope you'll
join us
for our next one dollar listening
practice seminar at polyglossa.com